<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The French King's appeal from the proceedings of the Pope to a general council, September 28, 1688 faithfully translated from the French copy printed at Paris.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49203</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12592024</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12592024</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63972</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49203)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63972)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 324:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The French King's appeal from the proceedings of the Pope to a general council, September 28, 1688 faithfully translated from the French copy printed at Paris.</title>
                  <author>Louis XIV, King of France, 1638-1715.</author>
                  <author>France. Parlement (Paris). Chambre des vacations.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Extract of Louis's appeal to Parliament, made to prevent retaliation by the Pope after Louis had expressed his grievances against him in a letter to Cardinal d'Estrées.</note>
                  <note>Translation of an unidentified work in French.</note>
                  <note>Caption title: Act of appeal made to the Future Council by the King's attorney general : and judgment given thereupon, by the Chamber of Vacation, the 27th of September, 1688.</note>
                  <note>Notarized by: Moussinot, Senior, &amp; Battelier.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715. --  Lettre du roy á Monsieur le Cardinal d'Estrées.</term>
               <term>Innocent --  XI, --  Pope, 1611-1689.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Foreign relations --  France.</term>
               <term>France --  Foreign relations --  Catholic Church.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63972:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
            <p>THE French King's APPEAL FROM THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE POPE TO A General Council, September 28. 1688.</p>
            <p>Faithfully Tranſlated from the French Copy Printed at <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="appeal_proceedings">
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:63972:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63972:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->
               <head>AN Act of Appeal Made to the <hi>Future Council,</hi> BY THE KING'S Attorney General; And Judgment given thereupon, by the Chamber of Vacation, the 27th. of <hi>September,</hi> 1688.</head>
               <head type="sub">An Extract from the Records of PARLIAMENT.</head>
               <p>THIS Day the King's Attorney General, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come into the <hi>Chamber of Vacation,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that the Matters of Fact laid open in the Letter the King ſent to the Cardinal <hi>d'Eſtrees</hi> the 6th. of this Month, having oblig'd his Majeſty
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63972:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->to repreſent to our Holy Father the Pope, that he cannot look upon him otherwiſe for time to come, than as a Prince that takes part with his Enemies, or own him for a Competent Judge in all Caſes wherein his intereſt may be concerned: The King's Attorney General has thought it his duty at the ſame time, to make uſe of the Precautions provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Law, practis'd in many Caſes, and founded on the Opinions of the <hi>Italian</hi> Cannoniſts themſelves, to prevent his Holineſs from paſſing any Valid and Regular Decrees in theſe Matters: With this purpoſe he hath made an Extrajudiciary Appeal from all the Proceedings his Holineſs may already have made, or make for time to come; and Decrees he may have paſs'd, or paſs for time to come, in prejudice to the King, the Rights of his Crown, and of the Subjects of his Majeſty: The Reſpect he ows to this Court, has oblig'd him to come and give them an account hereof, and to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to them the Act of Appeal he has made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon: They will eaſily perceive from the Command he has receiv'd from the King on this occaſion, the Piety, Wiſdom, and Moderation, which ſeem to have quite extinguiſhed in this Prince thoſe paſſions which ſo powerfully byaſs the reſt of Mankind. He hopes the Court will approve his Conduct herein; and is fully aſſured they will with abundance of zeal and faithfulneſs employ all the Authority the King has been pleas'd to truſt them with, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the reſpect due to his Majeſty upon ſo many juſt Titles; and to preſerve the Rights of his Crown, the peace of his Subjects, and thoſe Liberties which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63972:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->are not peculiar to the <hi>Gallican Church,</hi> but which ſhe has preſerved always with more Luſtre and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour than any other Church whatſoever.</p>
               <p>The Kings Attorney General being withdrawn, after having read the ſaid Act of Appeal with his Concluſions thereupon, by him left in the Office of the ſaid Court, and the Matter put to debate,</p>
               <p>The <hi>Chamber</hi> Orders, That the ſaid Act of Appeal ſhall be entred in the Office of Records, to reſort unto as occaſion ſhall be, and that moſt humble thanks be returned to his Majeſty; that he hath thought good his Attorney General ſhould begin thoſe Proceedings which have been practiſed upon the like occaſions: And that the firſt Preſident ſhall aſſure our ſaid Lord the King, in the Name of the Court, of their conſtant adherence to his Sacred Perſon and Service; and of their Zeal ever to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the Authority his Majeſty has been pleaſed to intruſt them with; in maintaining the Rights of the Crown, the Liberties of the Kingdom, and the Peace of his Subjects.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Given in <hi>Vacation,</hi> 
                     <date>the 27th. of <hi>September,</hi> 1688.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Signed <hi>DONGOIS:</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Before the Apoſtolical Notaries under-written, to that purpoſe ſent for to the Bar of the King's Council in the Palace of this City, my Lord <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les de Harlay</hi> made his perſonal appearance, and declared that the Repute of our Holy Father the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63972:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 11th. his Piety having made the King to look upon his Exaltation to the ſupreme Pontificate with much joy, his Majeſty has ever ſince endeavoured to joyn with his Holineſs, in labouring with one accord to promote the Concerns of the Glory and ſervice of God.</p>
               <p>That the King's deſires herein, and the ſteps he has already made in this matter having miſt of the good ſucceſs he might have expected from them, his Majeſty notwithſtanding has continued on his part to employ the Power God has entruſted him with, in preſerving the Purity of Faith within his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and in bringing back to the boſome of the Church a great number of the Children that were gone aſtray from her; and in affording her all the protection ſhe could expect from the Authority of a great King: His Majeſty having moreover at the ſame time edified her by his own example, and inſtructed all his Subjects by his ſingular Piety.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, our Holy Father the Pope, to whom ſo many Vertues and wonderful Acts ought particularly to have endeared the Perſon of the King, has with fervency embraced the Complaints that two Biſhops have made to him, concerning the Right of the Regale, having at the ſame time rejected the Atteſtations tendred him by all the other Biſhops of that Kingdom, concerning the favours they had received of the King in that regard, even in preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to his own Right.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:63972:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->
               <p>His Holineſs has deprived the King's Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours at the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> of thoſe very Franchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which they have enjoy'd during his Papacy, in a City where it might have been expected the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the Popes would have reſerved for our Kings thoſe more Illuſtrious and peculiar marks of Soveraignty, which they in former times diveſted themſelves of in favour of the Holy-See.</p>
               <p>Our Holy Father the Pope, has judg'd the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration which the Deputies of the Clergy aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the City 1682. made of their Opinions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Power of the Church, to be at leaſt a ſuſpitious and dangerous Doctrine, and at a Juncture wherein many of his Predeceſſours would rather have gone to the uttermoſt bounds of <hi>Europe,</hi> than to leave ſo many new Catholick Converts deſtitute of Paſtours: His Holineſs has refuſed his Bulls to many Eccleſiaſticks the King had nominated to fill the vacant Churches of his Kingdom; and to whom no other Crime can be imputed, than that of having known the Truth by their Learning, and declar'd the ſame with a ſincerity joyn'd with a great Reſpect for the Holy See.</p>
               <p>Our Holy Father the Pope's Behaviour for ſome Months ſince, in the Buſineſs of the Arch-Biſhoprick of <hi>Cologne,</hi> has given occaſion to Men to believe, that his Partial Dealings might as well raiſe as diſſipate a part of his Scruples and Difficulties.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:63972:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
               <p>His Holineſs perſiſting in his not owning, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſing Audience to an Ambaſſadour, whom the King was pleaſed to ſend at this Juncture, the Thunderbolts he has made uſe of againſt that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, the Interdiction of the Church dedicated to God under the Name of St. <hi>Lewis</hi> in the City of <hi>Rome;</hi> and laſt of all, his unheard of refuſing not long ſince to give Audience to a Perſon, whom the King had ſent to him on purpoſe, and even ſo much as to receive a Letter from his Majeſty, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ſaid Perſon was charged, will leave an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>moſt Incredible Inſtance to Poſterity, of the power that Religion, and the deſire of preſerving the Peace of Chriſtendom, have had over the heart of the King, as well as of the prevalence of preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice over the Spirit of the Pope, ſo contrary to the Obligations lying upon him from the place he fills.</p>
               <p>It would be to no purpoſe to enlarge here any further on this Subject, ſince the King has been pleaſed to permit, that his Letter writ on this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Cardinal <hi>D'Eſtrees</hi> the 6th of this Month, ſhould be publiſhed.</p>
               <p>And becauſe we ſee, that his Holineſs thus ſtops his Ears to all the Informations the King has been pleas'd to give him, as well as to the moſt juſt Complaints that were to be laid before him from his Majeſty, we are at laſt forced to ſtand up in our own Defence, to maintain the Dignity of the Crown,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63972:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->and the Peace of the King's Subjects by the Rule of Juſtice, at the ſame time that his Majeſty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms the ſame with ſo much Glory by the Puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of his Arms.</p>
               <p>And though we might Diſpence with entring any Proceedings againſt thoſe Decrees which would be null and void, by the condition of him that pronounces them, by the Quality of the Matters in Queſtion, and the Perſons they reſpect. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that his Majeſty may omit nothing of what is his Duty, and, according to the example of his Predeceſſours, the ſaid Attorny General doth as ſuch, and after having obtain'd Permiſſion from his Majeſty, declare that he makes his Appeal on behalf of the King and his Subjects to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council, which it ſhall pleaſe his Holineſs to Convene according to Canonical Form, from all the Proceedings and Acts of our Holy Father the Pope, and from any Decrees his Holineſs may have paſt ſince the notice given him by Order of his Majeſty, of the juſt Cauſes of complaint and exception he hath againſt the Perſon of his ſaid Holineſs, and in like manner from all other Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and Decrees he may make for the future, to the prejudice of his Majeſty, the Rights of his Crown and Subjects; proteſting at the ſame time, in the Name and by expreſs Command from the King, that his Intentions are ever to continue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably devoted to the Holy See, as to the true Centre of the Unity of the Church, to preſerve the Rights,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63972:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->Authorities, and Preeminencies thereof, with the ſame zeal his Majeſty has done on ſo many important Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, to render to the ſame himſelf, (and cauſing all his Subjects) the Reſpect, Deference, and Submiſſion due unto it, and that as ſoon as our Holy Father (being better informed) ſhall give Demonſtration of the Equity and Diſpoſition of a Judge and common Father, his Majeſty will pay (as he has done alwaies heretofore) to his very Perſon the Filial Duty he owes him, which the ſole Behaviour of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs forces him to forbear at preſent.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Given and paſt at <hi>Paris,</hi> in the Palace, at the Bar of King's Council, <date>in the year 1688. the 27th. of <hi>September,</hi>
                     </date> before Noon. Signed.</dateline>
                  <signed>Mouſſinor Senior &amp; Batteliée.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>And at the ſame time the foreſaid Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral made his Appearance in Preſence of the Apoſtolical Notaries at <hi>Paris</hi> underwritten, before the Reverend <hi>Nicholas Cheron,</hi> Prieſt Doctor in Divinity, and Official of the Arch-Biſhoprick of <hi>Paris,</hi> and after having tendred him the ſaid Act of Appeal by him made, and deſired to grant him the accuſtomed Letters to Summon, and the Party concern'd to proſecute the ſame when occaſion ſhall be, the ſaid Official hath as far as in him lyes, granted the ſaid Letters out of the reſpect he bears to the Univerſal Church, repreſented in a General Council, and in conſideration that the ſaid Appeal concerns the King's Rights, the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63972:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, and Peace of the Kingdom.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Given at the Hall of the Eccleſiaſtical Court of <hi>Paris,</hi> 
                     <date>in the Year 1688. the 27th of <hi>September,</hi> before Noon.</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <signed>Signed Mouſſinot Senior &amp; Battelier.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
